so you're saying earlier that's
interesting was that
what a person cannot get the right view
that first abandoning the value of
sensuality yeah
bending the value of sensuality is not
necessarily like abandoning sensuality
is it no that that there is what banning
such the retail not like not performing
central acts is not necessarily
abandoning sensuality you might be
abstained from engaging with sensuality
like sexuality and so on you might be
restrained there and celibate but you
are not abandoning the value of sense
pleasure which means you're not free
from sensuality even if you physically
withdrawn from it as the Buddha would
say but then those suitors we quoted in
the past where the Buddha would
establish laypeople over anybody else in
the right view there would be the thing
first generosity talk about a future
like goodness and so and so on and then
the Buddha would start talking teaching
them about the perils of sense desires
how little satisfaction they were so in
the nature sensuality he would teach
about that ah in its nature sense
desires are not worthy in its nature
sends desires of any kind engaging with
sense pleasures and seeking them out is
unwholesome regardless of what extent
and this is acceptable no in its nature
anything that pertains pertains to the
nature of sense desire must be abandoned
and then the right view would arise in
those people then it would teach them
this is suffering this is the origin of
suffering is own because for as long as
you don't abandon the value of sense
pleasures you're preventing the
necessary basis for the right view to be
established so even if those people
later on return to sensuality they never
return to the value of sensuality so
they might have returned to sensuality
if you know they have duties and
circumstances taking them back and so on
but they never valued it again which
means every time you're back in
sensuality they would have felt
uncomfortable and unpleasant so they
were still engaging with sense pleasures
despite having the right view and so on
but that's because they were satisfied
with the right view and they had many
things to do as they would say to the
world oh I have to excuse me now you
know I have many things to do in the
world say well do as you see fit but
more often than not actually in the
suitors people upon developing the
review would ask to go forth because the
life that's that's rooted and revolves
around central domain is meaningless it
always was me in English but now that
the whole thing became even more
apparent so like people would return to
it when you know they had big
responsibilities people didn't live
people's lives depending on them and so
on then they couldn't just ignore it but
even then there were a number of cases
who returned and then continued
practicing celibacy and looking after
their wives because they made the
promise they will but they said it's not
fitting for me now to engage in a sexual
intercourse with you and so on so what
is what is the value that's it the value
of pleasure that you get to your senses
so the sense objects are not a problem
the senses are not a problem even the
pleasures that arise on account of sense
objects and senses are not the problem
you valuing them desiring them
entertaining them protecting them
delighting in him that's the problem
so you have to abandon the value of
pleasure which means you have to be
willing to accept in that Universal
manner that for the rest of your life
sense pleasure is bad not to be engaged
with if you as I said before if you fail
to do it you might fail like in your act
as in you might sort of go back to
sensuality but you will not fail in
establishing the value that sensuality
is bad which means whenever you you fail
in in sustaining such acts of
renunciation you will feel guilty you
will feel ashamed so next time they will
protect you from doing it but they will
not protect you from doing it if you if
you never questioned the value of sense
pleasures if you basically even before
questioning it you start defending it
and justifying it means you're never
gonna prove it even if you live celibate
for the rest of your life because you're
prude sensuality by putting the value of
pleasure not by abstaining physically
from it of course abstaining physically
from it is a necessary basis for you to
see the value of it and then you can
approve it but in itself it will not
automatically result in it so the value
of of basically it's like learning to
see that by the way all the sense
pleasures are addictive definition of
addiction means definition of sense
domain sensual domain so all these
different addictions share that same
nature in terms in themselves they are
sensual they provide sense pleasure
so obviously sexuality and that kind of
deeply rooted central needs are the the
greatest of all addictions but as any
other addiction if you abstain from it
it will become more apparent for what it
is the only reason you're not seeing
your addiction is because you refuse to
give it up but if you start having
reasons for giving it up then you get to
see how really addictive you are you're
never gonna see how addicted to
cigarettes or heroin you are until you
try and quit it then you feel the weight
of it
so the the necessary step for giving up
addiction is to give it up
stop doing it inactive will act the will
to abstain yourself physically from
engaging with it and then the value of
it will become more apparent which means
you have to accept pure unadulterated
pain of betrayal there has to be the
first step and not just accept it for a
week or for 10 days you have to accept
it universally you don't know how long
it will last
it doesn't matter sensuality will never
be valuable even as something they could
free you from that pain which is kind of
the inherent value of sensuality not
just the provides with pleasure
it provides you the only form of escape
from pain that you know as the Buddha
said which means even if you don't value
sensual pleasures like you don't value
objects of your senses you value
sensuality as the means of escape from
discomfort and that's already around
good that's already a problem
so if you accept then the value for
rather if you see through the apparent
value of sensuality and see it as non
valuable as something to not be
delighted something dangerous something
or worthy all those descriptions the
Buddha would talk about and you have to
accept then the pain they will come out
of it
you kind of know it we're not going to
last for the rest of your life
let's see hoping that it doesn't last
for the rest of your life means
implicitly hoping that you can return
back to sensuality and you must never
accept sensuality even in the utmost
remote future the nature of sensuality
is always perilous always not worried
delighting in always dangerous which
means in this life and lives to come any
future they will never be crossing
between the domain of me wanting
sensuality and being free from
centrality and then you you see the pain
might not even last that long but you
have to accept it as if it's going to
last forever because if you don't to
that extent you're still valuing
sensuality as freedom from pain
and that all those passages we quota
deposits exactly what is cut he will
make people understand the danger of the
sense desires not this sense in the
desire or half of that sense desire in
its nature the act of sense
chasing sense pleasure going after scent
valuing sense pleasure that's already
White's dangerous so you make people
understand that so fully understanding
it abandoning it at that universal level
even if you physically remain still
attracted and can lapse due to
carelessness and go back to sensuality
you'll never go back to the value of
sensuality they would then dictate your
whole life which is the case with most
of the people
to see in the extent
of the gratification in sensuality yeah
seeing the extent of gratification is
the extent of what's valuable in
sensuality for you so that is its extent
of its gratification so you have to try
and find out what yeah you have to
understand why you are attracted to
sensuality not in a psychologizing man
out because my hormones no no why do you
value mentally pleasures of the senses
why can you just not value them because
you never try to not value them you're
always taking it for granted and value
them for their pleasure is always
regarded as good pleasure of senses only
when he gets a bit excessive you can say
okay now it's a bit much no no you don't
want your value to depend on the
quantity or even quality of the pleasure
doesn't matter if it's lofty as the
Buddha say if it's heavenly
if it slowly like animal realm doesn't
matter if it's little if it's a lot the
cyclic little bit of excrement same
smells as bad as the full truckload of
it
same with sensuality a little bit of it
shares the same nature of perilous
danger not worth adhering to and
engaging with there's no matter how we
find and that's in that suit that the
perfect types of celibacy the Buddha
talks but first is you don't have sexual
intercourse then second you don't touch
women do you don't let them touch you
then you don't talk to them then you
don't go and listen to them then you
don't think about them and then you
don't think about the pleasure of
heavens and so on that you will get
through such perfect restraint if you if
you withdraw yourself from all these
wanting of this pleasure that's the
perfect syllabus perfect brahmacari as a
village driver and then the only course
left for you is to uproot your addiction
to pleasure of any time
and there is no way you would be able to
reevaluate the value of sensuality
unless you first physically be drawn
from it unless you take on the sensory
strength in the presets and really we
are talking about eight precepts five
precepts is how you should live your
life they would separate you from an
animal but five precepts is not a basis
for understanding five priests it is the
lowest minimum threshold of a house in
life but that doesn't mean you can get
wisdom on account of the minimum
threshold of a wholesome life but yes if
you haven't kept any pieces whatsoever
yet five is a good place to start so the
value in sensuality hmm you said it
provides a gratification a pleasure of
some kind of distracting myself from the
fact that it's unpleasant not satisfied
yeah well I'm value of sensuality is
that it provides you a pleasure from the
pain of itself sensuality touches you
with pain but at the same time it offers
a solution for that pain but like
racketeering hey if you pay me I'll make
your problems go away problems that I
put on you so that you will pay me so
you can wreck it by your own sensuality
your own desires and the more you pay
the more they're gonna come knocking cuz
Esau is susceptible let's push him let's
bleed him dry it's exactly what's in
Charlie that's it until you draw a line
for yourself
and then in the other pain but if you're
not making it worse
that's the thing first thing people fear
if I stop
going off to these pleasures in sexual
sexual type pleasures somehow something
Bad's going to happen something really
yeah because you're not just giving up
this pleasure of that pleasure by giving
up value of sensuality you're giving up
the value of the entire world of
sensuality which means and that's the
nature of any addiction the reason why
addictions are hard to give up you're
not giving them up specifically you're
giving up the whole world you lived
through them whether it's alcohol
cigarettes drugs doesn't matter the
reason they're pleasant is because you
get to experience the whole world on the
basis of that substance or that
addiction or that pleasure Aaron is not
pleasant in itself experiencing the
world through heroin is where that
pleasure comes from that peace
undisturbed the greatest whatever it is
the people will be addicted to its
defined by the experience of the world
on account of it that's why you
literally basically lose any and
complete interest in the world because
you stopped feeling anything in regard
to which is what we all want to do from
the start everybody wants peace
everybody wants known disturbance and
now you found the substance that
provides you with utmost pleasure
whereby nothing can disturb you for as
long is a substance lost but you only
get that non disturbance gets defined by
the disturbance that doesn't disturb you
anymore and when I say the world defines
the other one you need to go and seek it
out your senses are your world so your
senses stop disturbing you if you are
high on drugs for example and that's why
it gets so painful that withdrawal from
that sense pleasures because you'll be
drawing from the only world you know so
it feels like dying more often than not
the same with cigarettes by the way you
smoke a cigarette you literally inhaling
the whole world through them as Assad -
described in his book and it's it's
absolutely true everything everything
that you've been doing you've been doing
on the basis of possibility of that
pleasure and during of that try and
imagine now you want to also put sexual
pleasure which is far more rooted than
any in a drug you can be addicted to so you
in a drug you can be addicted to so you
will need to have a pretty strong reason
for that otherwise there's no way you'll
succeed so that's what I mean like even
if you don't succeed in doing it you
must not dilute the reasons for doing it
because if you do that that for sure you
will not succeed if you start devaluing
the non value of sensuality means you're
automatically valuing sensuality so if
you say no no no I don't need to be
restrained and I can practice them at
the same time means I don't need to
basically abandon the value of
sensuality and at the same time I can
practice number what is number well dumb
is the dispassion in freedom from
sexuality so you're saying you cannot
devalue sensuality and by not devaluing
it you are devaluing it that's a plain
after direct contradiction and that's
what the Buddha said even to people who
are not necessarily following his
teachings when they asking what criteria
should they use for good advices
whatever leads without practice leads to
dispassion disenchantment abandoning renunciation
disenchantment abandoning renunciation
you should fall you should value it's
more valuable you should do it so what
celibacy or non celibacy which one leads
to dispassion sense restraint or non
sense restraint which one leads to
disenchantment well the answer is
straightforward and now you can say yeah
but it's too much for me
ok that's fine you too weak you admit
you're too weak and that's the necessary
basis for developing strength
recognizing your weakness but if you say
no no I don't need to be sense restraint
that's it
you just throw away the whole thing now
and you stay weak same like people say I
can give up smoking whenever I want but
you can't want to give up smoking
whenever you want and without wanting to
give up smoking without removing the
value of smoking you will never give it
up I can stop smoking when I want to
stop yeah but I can't want to stop
yes and surely I can be restrained yeah
but you can't want to be restrained
because if you can you will take it on
in that Universal manner because I
essentiality is never worth engaging
with I know it's bad but I don't think
but it's not that bad
yes exactly I know it's not as valuable
as it presents itself but it's not that
unavailable either I got nothing else
I'm not seeing the danger of it you're
not seeing the pedal but I need
something to replace exactly which means
I need to something to replace the
vacuum left by removing the content of
that which I value which means you never
devalue it you just replace it replace
one addiction with the other you're
still addicted but then maybe if I
replace my addiction was there they find
it refine my addiction
so relative set of drugs I turn to God
see that's fine as long as you don't
ignore the value of your addiction at
the expense of it in other words yes let
me replace my non precept keeping with
five presets
it's still better but let me not develop
the view that 5pc will be enough for me
to devalue my addiction because it's not
so if you don't develop the view then
it's fine then you can refine your five
precepts on to eight places then a trace
of to 10 trips and so on the common
thread through all of that is you
wanting to be free from the value of
sensuality but if you replace five
precepts if you replace your non piece
of your five precepts and say that said
see I have accomplished the restraint
means now and now you mask the fact that
there is still a lot more to be done in
order to approve the value of sensuality
so yes you can replace your addiction
with God or whatever you want but don't
entertain the notion that you are
completely free from addiction and most
people recommend a level they don't do
that remember like you saw that people
would say I once an addict you remain
and adding for the rest of your life is
just a question of managing and not
returning back to the addiction
literally means you remain valuing
sensuality for the rest of your life now
you recognize it
particular forms of the sensuality of
worse than the other such as heroin or
any other drugs resulted in far great
reaching adverse consequences but you
still value pleasure of senses and for
that you need more than just the
determination of I'll give up this drug
or dead drug you need to understand that
has to pertain for the rest of your life
and has to be seen in its nature as
dangerous not worthy and that pleasure
it's actually pain and then you'll be
able to do unvalued devalue it so there
is it like practice common practice of a
super practice this is therefore
devaluing yeah that's those things that
you are yeah it can help you initially
exactly people see people don't see the
nature of the value of pleasure which
means they only see the object of their
pleasure blindly so you practiced our
practicing sense restraint you will
still value the objects of your pleasure
then you might want to devalue them a
bit by seeing them for what they really
are that's where the tsuba is showing
you the unattractive basis of everything
that you can find attractive but a tsuba
in itself exactly can also become a
wrong thing then because in itself it
will not lead you to devalue your
dependence on pleasure which is not in
sense objects nor in your senses in your
it's in your attitude towards
possibility of pleasure okay I renounce
these pleasures because they are not
good but you still value other pleasures
they might come along that's a degree to
me you don't need to sit and think about
pleasures of heaven and rationalize them
no just by implying that there are other
pleasures body adhering to accept these
ones that you renounced you establish
yourself upon that value which means
it's not sensuality is not devalued in
that Universal manner pleasure of any
kind doesn't matter if I see things that
are agreeable or disagreeable
what matters is pleasure did I get an
account of it and seeking them out on
account of wanting that pleasure will
come from them
so your dependence on the your own
pleasure of your own senses it's
completely gratuitous and internal and
not to be found in the world it's just
you have it's a view you value the
pleasure you assume them as valuable
that's why we decoded Upali one of the
coordinates and that's why even Apple -
janaki free himself from sensuality if
he were to find a good enough reason to
see that any form of sexual activity any
form of sensors and sensual pleasure is
always unwholesome always bad not to be
welcomed not to be engaged with and
stick to it he would get to see the true
nature of it which is dangerous not to
be welcomed not to be engaged so the
only reason people engage with
sensuality is because they don't see
that the danger of it of that same thing
so the only reason a person enjoys is
beautiful beverage as I said this is
because you don't understand that it's
poisonous if you understand it it's
poisonous by the way poison is
undetectable so what's the difference
then between a poisonous drink it should
oh no it's poisonous and it you know
it's poisonous it's the knowledge in
regard to it that's different you know
that it's poisonous no the pleasure the
taste has remained perfect but you now
completely don't want it because you
know it's the poison that pleasure is
the poison not like there is a hidden
poison that I can extract from the
pleasure and still have the pleasure
pleasure is the poison that's it you
regard pleasure is a poison or is a
painful dart is the Buddha would say you
will lose any attraction towards it how
long do you have to regard it like that
well you don't know but you have to take
it in the ultimate sense not likely let
me do it for a week and become a Nogami
and then I have to I can go back to my
life or something that's it that's how
you also get to learn from your sense
restraint devalue things they need to be
developed not just blindly adhere to it you